<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming on Elliot Snow-Kropla</title>
    <link>http://ejsk.ca/tags/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Programming on Elliot Snow-Kropla</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Elliot Snow-Kropla</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2017 18:32:47 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ejsk.ca/tags/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Rust Web-Development</title>
      <link>http://ejsk.ca/post/rust-web2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2017 18:32:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ejsk.ca/post/rust-web2/</guid>
      <description>This entry will be a little scattershot, just some miscellaneous thoughts and impressions.
Interacting with APIs It&amp;rsquo;s a little inconvenient to be making a lot of little structs for each feature of an API; where in JavaScript or Python you would have a dictionary, if you want type safety you need to make a struct with the proper fields. Strictly speaking you don&amp;rsquo;t need to; operating on untyped JSON is actually fairly straightforward, but when you know that the rest of your codebase isn&amp;rsquo;t going to crash the parts that aren&amp;rsquo;t guarenteed by the compiler niggle in your brain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rust Web-Development, Part 1</title>
      <link>http://ejsk.ca/post/rust-web/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 10:43:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ejsk.ca/post/rust-web/</guid>
      <description>Now that Hairy Little Buggers is wrapped up, I figured I&amp;rsquo;d use my sabbatical to dive into web-development. This is also a good chance to play with Rust again; the last time I checked it out was before 1.0 when I was playing with the Matasano crypto challenges, so it will be interesting to see how much more mature the ecosystem is.
Now, I don&amp;rsquo;t really know anything about web-development, so after a little research I picked up Flask Web Development based on the Flask Mega-Tutorial.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>